{
  "text": "CHAPTER III. MUSIC AMONG THE ANCIENT GREEKS Upon several accounts the development of the art of music among the ancient Greeks is both important and interesting. Our word music is theirs. It carries with its etymology the derivation from the Muses, the nine agreeable divinities who presided over the more becoming and nobler activities of the Greek mind. By music the Greeks meant much more than merely the tonal art itself. Under this term they included, pretty much, all that they had of a liberal education. Grammar, history, rhetoric, mathematics, poetry and song, all were included in this one elastic and comprehensive term. Music itself, the art of tone sequence, they called harmony. Our information concerning the general course of the development of music among this people is pretty accurate, through a period of about 1300 years. The entire course of the Greek history of music may be divided into four great divisions, each of which was principally devoted to a certain part of the art. These divisions begin at a date which we might take approximately at about 1000 BC, when Homeric poems began to be chanted or sung by traveling minstrels called Rhapsodists. The schools of Rhapsodies lasted for about 250 years, when choral and patriotic song began to be developed. In connection with this part of the history, there was, in the later portion of it, a more ornamental and fanciful development of the smaller and social uses of song, represented by Sappho, Anacreon and others. This period endured for about two centuries and a half, and by insensible degrees passed into the Attic drama, which came to its maturity at the hands of Aeschylus, and Euripides about 450 BC. Here was the culmination of Greek musical art, upon the purely artistic and aesthetic side. Then followed a period of philosophizing, theory and mathematical deduction, which extended to the end of the Alexandrian schools about 300 AD. The limits of the present work do not permit tracing this course of progress with the amplitude which its relation to liberal education would otherwise warrant, or even to the extent which its bearing upon the present ideals of the tonal art would justify, were not the range of subjects indispensable to even a summarized treatment of musical history so wide as it has now become, but the general features of the different steps of the Greek music are the following. As already noticed, the earliest traces of music are those in the Homeric poems, which are thought to have been composed about 1000 BC. In these we find the minstrel everywhere a central figure, an honored guest, ready at call to entertain the company with some ballad of the ancient times, or to improvise a new one appropriate to the case in hand. The heroes themselves were not loath to take part in these exercises. Ulysses, the Odyssey tells us, occasionally took the lyre in his own hand and sang a rhapsody of his own adventures. Several centuries later, Solon, one of the famed seven wise men of Greece, composed a rhapsody of Salamis, or the Lost Island, and sang it in a public assembly of the Athenians with so much effect that an expedition was organized, with Solon at its head, for its recovery which presently followed triumphantly. Many passages in the Odyssey will occur to the classical reader in illustration of the position of the minstrels in Argos in the earlier times, for example, Odyssey 1.400, Bryant's translation. Silent all, they set and listened to the illustrious Bard, who sang of the calamitous return of the Greek host from Troy at the command of Pallas. From her chamber o'er the hall the daughter of Vicarius, the sage queen Penelope, had heard the heavenly strain, and knew its theme. Down by the lofty stairs she came, but not alone, there followed her two maidens. When the glorious lady reached the threshold of the strong-built hall, were set the suitors, holding up a delicate veil before her face, and with a gush of tears the queen bespake the sacred minstrel thus, Fimius, thou know'st many a pleasing theme, the deeds of gods and heroes such as Bards are wont to celebrate, take then thy place and sing of one of these, and let the guests in silence drink the wine. But cease this strain, it is too sad it cuts me to the heart, and wakes a sorrow without bounds, such grief I bear for him, my lord, of whom I think continually, whose glory is abroad through Hellas and through Argos everywhere. And then Telemachus, the prudent, spake, why, O my mother, canst thou not endure that thus the well-graced poet should delight his hearers with a theme to which his mind is inly moved The Bards deserve no blame, Jove is the cause, for he at will inspires the lay that each must sing. Later than the Homeric Rhapsodists, the Hesiodic poems were composed and sung similarly by wandering minstrels, who, although wandering, were not on that account lowly esteemed. There were regular schools or, more properly, guilds of Rhapsodists, into which only those were admitted as masters, who were able to treat the current topics with the light and inspiring touch of real poetry, and only those taken as apprentices, who evinced proper talent and promise. The training of these schools was long, partly spent in acquiring technique of treating subjects, and the mastery of the lyre, and partly in memorizing the Homeric and Hesiodic hymns. It is supposed that these poems were transmitted for more than three centuries orally in this way, before having been reduced to writing. In Hesiod's poem of the Shield of Hercules, Banks Translation, 365, the general idea of the Greek festive processions is illustrated. There men in dances and in festive joys held revelry. Some on the smooth-wheeled car a virgin bride conducted, then burst forth aloud the marriage song, and far and wide long splendors flashed from many a quivering torch born in the hands of slaves. Gay, blooming girls preceded, and the dancers followed blithe, these with shrill pipe indenting the soft lip-breathed melody, while broken echoes thrilled around them to the lyre with flying touch. Those led the love-enkindled dance. A group of youths was elsewhere imaged, to the flute desporting, some in dances and in song, in laughter others, to the minstrel's flute so past they on, and the whole city seemed as filled with pomps, with dances, and with feasts. So again, in the same poem, 274, there is a scene of a minstrel contest among the immortal gods themselves, described by the poet from one of the scenes upon the shield of Hercules. And the tuneful choir appeared of heaven's immortals, in the midst the son of Job and of Latona sweetly rang upon his golden harp, the Olympian mount, dwelling of gods, thrilled back the broken sound, and there were seen the assembly of the gods listening, encircled with beatitude, and in sweet contests with Apollo, there the virgins of Pieria raised the strain, preluding, and they seemed as though they sang with clear sonorous voices. As early as 750 BC, we find the famous rhapsodist Terpander summoned to Sparta to sing patriotic songs in the hope of preventing a secession of this rather unruly state. He accomplished his mission a circumstance creditable alike to the talent of the poet minstrel and the high estimation in which the class was held. The application of music to patriotic purposes was no novelty. Plutarch, in his Life of Lycurgus, says that Thales was famed for his wisdom and his political abilities. He was, withal, a lyric poet who, under cover of exercising his art, performed as great things as the most excellent lawgivers, for his odes were so many persuasions to obedience and unanimity, as by means of numbers they had great grace and power, they softened insensibly the manners of the audience, drew them off from the animosities which then prevailed, and united them in zeal for excellence and virtue. Again, of the subject matter of the Spartan songs, he says, their songs had a spirit which could arouse the soul and impel to an enthusiastic action. The language was plain and manly, the subjects serious and moral, for they consisted chiefly of praises of heroes who had died for Sparta, or else of expressions of detestation for such wretches as had declined the glorious privilege. About this time, the art of choral song began to be much cultivated in Greece, particularly in connection with the cult of certain divinities, especially Dionysos and Apollo. By the term choral song, we are not to understand anything resembling our singing of a chorus in parts. There was no part singing in Greece, but merely a singing or rather chanting of national and patriotic songs in unison, accompanied by the sitara, the national instrument. Plato speaks of the imitative and semi-dramatic character of the choral dance, Laws 2.655. Choric movements are imitations of manners occurring in various actions, chances, characters. Each particular is imitated, and those to whom the words, the songs or dances are suited, either by nature or habit, or both, cannot help feeling pleasure in them and calling them beautiful. About 500 BC, a room was rented upon the marketplace for the practice of the chorus. Every town had its body of singers, who sang and performed the evolutions of the representative dance appropriate to the service of the particular divinity to whom they were devoted. Presently, competitive singing came into vogue, in connection with the famous games, and the art of the poet was taxed, as well as the musical and more purely vocal arts of the singers themselves, striving in honorable competition for the glory of their native towns. In some of the festival occasions, the proceedings of the choral songs were varied by the leader, who improvised rhapsodies upon topics connected with the life of the divinity, or upon national stories. At proper points, the chorus came in with a refrain, which remained a fixed quantity, being put in, apparently, at whatever points the inspiration of breath of the leader needed a point of repose. None of these compositions have come down to us, but the allusions to them in ancient writings give, perhaps, a sufficiently accurate idea of their nature. The added interest incident to the fresh improvisations of the leader, in this form of choral song, presently opened toward a lyric drama. Thespis is credited with having been the first to place the leader upon a centrally located stage where he could be plainly seen and heard by all concerned. Now the recitations became more dramatic, the choruses more varied, the speaker illustrated by gestures the acts which he described. He varied his style of delivery according to the feeling appropriate to the incidents represented. The chorus, meanwhile, was not upon the stage, but in a central location below, and during their strophes they circled around the platform of the leader in a sort of mystic dance, each man accompanying himself upon his sitara. From this to adding a second speaker to the one already upon the stage was but a short step. It was taken, and the result was a drama with a chorus in connection. In the earlier plays the speakers represented as many characters as necessary for carrying out the action. Later they changed costume to some extent, the chorus, meanwhile, occupying the time with their own songs which generally had the character of a comment upon the action as developed at the moment. The changes of costume were extremely slight, merely a different headdress, a mantle, or some slight modification of appearance, more or less symbolical in character. All the dialogue was delivered in a musical voice, and it is thought all accompanied by the sitara which every player carried in his hand. The instrument was sometimes played all the time, in the same notes as those of the song or chant. At other times the speaker employed it for ritournelles, for affording breathing time, or points of emphasis. Once in a great while, it is thought, the instrument had a note different from that of the song in connection with it. Upon this point great uncertainty prevails. At length, about 470 B.C., Aeschylus the Great Tragedian made his debut as actor and author, and placed three speakers upon the stage. Besides the three principals, each man had a suite. If his station demanded such an appendage according to the ideas or customs of the times. These, however, had the rank of supernumeraries, merely following the speaker around, but never taking part in the dialogue. The principals each represented more than one character, effecting some slight change of costume for indicating the transformation. The stage was simply an open platform with three doors in the rear. The actor entered by one door, represented a prince at home, from another a prince abroad. By another door he represented a common person. The chorus occupied the central place in front of the stage, much in the same location as the parquet is now. In the center of this space was an altar originally dedicated to Dionysus, and an offering was probably placed upon it. Later, the choreagos, or leader of the chorus, sat upon it and directed the movements of the singers, much as the operatic director does now. The theatres were very large, being vast amphitheatres, open to the sky, but with an awning available over the more expensive seats. The seats were of stone, arranged exactly like those in a modern circus. The theatre in Athens is said to have held 25,000 persons. At first admission was free, the theatre being conducted by the state. The plays were mounted very expensively at times, although with the absence of scenery or properties of an elaborate character, it is not easy to imagine what was the use made of the vast sums reported to have been expended in different productions. There was a rivalry of leading citizens, each taking upon himself the expense of mounting a new play and striving to outdo the last before him upon the list. There were three great dramatic authors whose names have come down to us as the Shakespeare's of the Athenian drama. They were Aeschylus, Sophocles and Euripides. All were great poets, the first perhaps the greatest. Sophocles was a fine musician and an elegant poet, and for many years he remained the popular idol. All these men wrote not only the words of the plays, but the music as well, every phrase, every character having been noted for musical utterance, and all the choral effects carefully planned. Besides this he composed what was then called the Orchestic, whence we have our word orchestra. By Orchestic they meant an apparatus of mystical dancing or posturing, and marching, and certain gestures. We do not know precisely what this famous Orchestic was, for no example of it has come down to us in intelligible form, but from the descriptions of it by contemporary writers, it seems to have formed the pantomimic complement of the acting, with a certain added grace of art in grouping and posturing, suited to attract and satisfy the eye of a public accustomed to national games, and the beautiful conceptions of Phidias upon the Parthenon freeze. Thus, as will be readily seen, this drama was essentially opera. For reasons to be hereafter detailed, the music is thought to have been of slight tonal value. This is inferred from the compass of the instruments, and the general deficiency of the Greeks upon this side, although popular report assigns them a place entirely different. This mystical drama, leaving so much to the imagination, and supplementing its actual representation by the help of chorus, and a sort of sanctity derived from music, lasted but a few years. Other causes were at work destined to bring it to a close, almost immediately after Euripides appeared the great comedy writer Aristophanes, about 420 BC. This great artist was not simply a dramatist, but also a patriot and a philosopher. In several of his plays he satirizes the classical dramas effectively, parodies their effects, and in general pokes fun at them. He was, however, a well-accomplished musician who might, if he had chosen, have gone on in the steps of his predecessors. But the times were not favorable to this. Previous to the time of Socrates, orators in addressing popular assemblies, lawyers in pleading cases, and all public speakers appear to have made use of the sitara as a sort of accompaniment, if for no other purpose than to assure themselves of securing a proper pitch of the voice. But Socrates drew attention to verbal distinctions, made words the image of exact concepts, and in general set in operation an era of scientific classification and purely intellectual development into which music could not enter, especially in a form so poor upon the tonal side as Greek art then was, and always remained. Then came the great orators, of whom Demosthenes was the greatest, who seems to have been the first to speak without musical aids, and Plato, with his philosophy, and after him the great Aristotle, the father of scientific classification and orderly knowledge. To a disciple of Aristotle, Aristoxenus, we are indebted for the first really musical work which has come down to us. It is true that the so-called problems of Aristotle contain many of a musical character, showing that this great master observed tonal effects in a purely musical spirit, but he did not make a scientific treatise upon the art. In his politics he has much admirable matter relating to music, and its influence upon the feelings and its office in life has hardly been better explained than by him, but music upon the practical side remained a sealed book. Among the lucid musical questions of Aristotle's problems, which, if not by Aristotle himself, are at least the product of his time or the succeeding century, he refers to the phenomena of sympathetic resonance. He asks, further, why it is that when meza, the keynote of the lyre, is out of tune, everything is out of tune, yet when any other string is out of tune, it affects only the particular string which is not correctly adjusted. One of his most instructive, but also, as it turned out, most misleading questions was why they did not magadize, sing in, fourths and fifths as well as in octaves, since the consonances of the fourth and the fifth are almost as well sounding as those of the octave. This question appears to have led to the practice of what Huchbald called diaphony. This question, it may be remarked incidentally, is conclusive that they did not use the third as a consonance in Aristotle's time, nor sing together in fourths, fifths or any other intervals than the octave. In spite of the talk about music by the Greek writers, musical theory in an exact form occupies but a small place in the volume of their works. The earliest theorist of whom we have any account was Pythagoras, who lived about 580 BC. He was one of the first of the Greek wise men to avail himself of the opening of Egypt to foreigners which took place by Psammeticus I in the year 600 BC. Pythagoras lived there 20 years in connection with one of the temples where he seems to have gained the confidence of the priesthood and learned much of his philosophy and so-called musical science. He defined the mathematical relation of the octave as produced by half of a given string, the fifth produced by two-thirds and the fourth by three-fourths. He also found the ratio of the major step by subtracting the fourth from the fifth. This was the ratio 9 to 8. With this as a measure he attempted to place the tones of the tetrachord, or Greek scale of four tones, which was the unit of their tonal system. This gave him two major steps and a half-step, somewhat too small, being equal to the ratio of 256 to 243. The most important part of Pythagoras' influence upon the art of music was of a sentimental character. From Egypt he acquired many ideas of a musical nature such as that certain tones represented the planets and that time was the essence of all things. It was one of the laws of his religion that before retiring at night his disciples should sing a hymn in order to compose their spirits and prepare them for rest. The verses selected for this use were probably of a devotional character like what are now known as the Orphic hymns, of which the lines upon the next page may be taken as a specimen. Ambrose well remarks that such hymns could only have been sung appropriately to melodies of a choral-like character. Thou ruler of the sea, the sky, the vast abyss, Thou who shatterest the heavens with Thy thunder-peals, Thou before whom spirits fall in awe and gods do tremble, Thou to whom fates belong, So wise, so unrelenting, Thou draw near and shine in us. Various musicians and theorists later are credited with having made additions to the musical resources of the Greeks, and it was a proverb said of any smart man that he added a new string to the lyre. This was said of Terpander especially, but it is pretty certain that the lyre had six or seven strings sometime before Terpander, and that the form of expression was purely symbolical. As if they had said of him, he set the river on fire. The first real contributions to musical science after the problems of Aristotle already cited are the two works of his pupil Aristoxenus, one on harmony, the other on rhythm. These give a full account of the Greek musical systems and are the source of the greater part of our information upon the subject. From them it appears that the basis of their scale was the tetrachord of four tones placed at an interval of two steps and a half-step. The outside tones of the tetrachord remained fixed upon the lyre, but the two middle ones were varied for the purpose of modulation. The Dorian tetrachord corresponded to our succession Mi-Fa-So-La, the Phrygian Re-Mi-Fa-So, the Lydian Frum-Do. Besides these modes, the Greeks had what they called genera, of which there were three, the diatonic, to which the examples already given belong, the chromatic, in which the tetrachord had the form of Mi-Fa-Fi-La, the interval between the two upper tones being equal to a step and a half, and the enharmonic, in which the first two intervals were one quarter of a step and the upper one a major third. We are entirely ignorant of the practical use made of these different forms of scale. Whether the quartered tones were used habitually or were glided, like apogiaturas, or passing tones, has been vigorously maintained on both sides by different writers. The evidence seems to point to the enharmonic as having been the most ancient, and the chromatic and diatonic gradually superseding it. In Plato, Aristotle and many of the Greek writers, especially in Athenaeus, much is said about the characteristic expression of the different modes, but as they are mutually contradictory, one saying of a given mode that it is bold and manly, while another calls it feeble and innervating, we may leave this for the antiquarians to settle for themselves. After Aristotle, there were several Greek theorists who devoted themselves to mathematical computations, the favorite problem seeming to be to find as many ways as possible of dividing the major fourth, or the ratio 4 to 3, into what they called super-particular ratios, that is to say a series of fractions in which each numerator differed from the denominator by unity. They had observed that all the ratios discovered by Pythagoras had this character, 1 to 2, 2 to 3, 3 to 4, 8 to 9, and they attributed magical properties to the fact, and sought to demonstrate the entire theory of music by the production of similar combinations. The latest writer of the Greek school was Claudius Ptolemy, who lived at Alexandria about 150 A.D. In his work upon harmony, he gives a very large number of tables of fractions of this kind, his own and those of all previous Greek theorists, and it is to his book that we principally owe all the exact knowledge of Greek musical theory which we possess. Among other computations, Ptolemy gives the precise formula of the first four notes of the scale as we now have it, but as this occurred only as one among many of a similar character, and is in no way distinguished from any of the others by any adjective implying greater confidence in it, we can only count it as a lucky accident. The eminence that has been awarded to Ptolemy as the original discoverer of the correct ratio of the major scale, therefore does not properly belong to him. This will more clearly appear from the entire table of the various determinations of the diatonic mode made by Ptolemy, taken from his work, edition by John Wallace, Oxford, 1682, pages 88 and 172. He gives no less than five of his own forms of diatonic genus, as follows. The fractions give vibration ratios. Soft diatonic, 8 to 7, by 10 to 9, by 12 to 12, equals 4 to 3. Medium diatonic, 9 to 8, by 8 to 7, by 28 to 27, equals 4 to 3. Intense diatonic, 10 to 9, by 9 to 8, by 16 to 15, equals 4 to 3. Equable diatonic, 10 to 8, to 9, by 11 to 10, by 12 to 11, equals 4 to 3. Diatonic, diatonic, 9 to 8, by 9 to 8, by 256 to 243, equals 4 to 3. Among these, there is no one that is correct or rational. The proper ratios are given in the diatonic in tense, but the large and small steps stand in the wrong order. It is in Ptolemy's record of the determinations of Didymus, born at Alexandria, 63 B.C., that the true tuning of the first four tones of the scale occurs. This is it, diatonic Didymus, 9 to 8, by 10 to 9, by 16 to 15, equals 4 to 3. Thus it appears that it was Didymus, and not Ptolemy, who proposed the tuning of the tetrachord, which is now accepted as correct. It is very evident from the entire course of the discussion as conducted by Ptolemy, that his calculations were purely abstract. He is to be reckoned among the Pythagoreans, who held that in time and number all things consist. It was not until some centuries later, that the happy thought of Didymus came to recognition as the true statement of the mathematical relation of the first four tones of the scale, and then only through the ears of a race of musicians following the great theses of Aristoxenus, that in music it is always the ear which must be the arbiter, and not abstract reasoning or calculation. The ratios of the major and minor third also occur among the calculations of Didymus, but here again they count for nothing in the history of all music. Here again they count for nothing in the history of art, because these intervals derive their value and expressive quality from their harmonic relation, while Didymus and all the Greeks employed them as melodic skips only, and reckoned them in with a multitude of other skips and progressions, without distinguishing them in any way. The one characteristic instrument of Greek music from the earliest to the latest days was the lyre. In the oldest times, those of Homer and Hesiod, it was called formynx, which is believed to have been the form so often represented on Greek vases of a turtle shell with side pieces like horns, an instrument having but little effective resonance. The later form was the so-called sitara, the most common shape of which is that made familiar to all by the pedal piece of the square pianoforte. This instrument rarely had more than six strings, and as it had no fingerboard, it could have had no more notes than strings. Chappell, the English historian, attempts to demonstrate that certain ones of these instruments had a bridge, dividing the strings into two parts, thus largely increasing the compass, but the evidence supporting this hypothesis is not satisfactory. Plato speaks of instruments of many strings imported from Asia, which seem to have been the fashion or fad in his day. He disapproved of them very heartily, but the terms in which he speaks of them show that he cannot have been very familiar with their appearance, for it is impossible to make out what he is driving at. There is considerable doubt as to the extent to which the larger instruments of Asiatic origin penetrated the general musical practice of Greece. Athenaeus, in his Banquets of the Learned, open parenthesis B, period, Roman numeral XVI, comma, C, close parenthesis, comma, quotes Anacreon as saying, I hold my Magadis and sing, striking loud the twentieth string, Leucapsis, at the rapid hour leads you to youth, and beauties bower. Most certainly the lyre of Terpander had no twenty strings. The so-called Greek flute was a very reedy oboe or clarinet, a pipe played with a reed, the pitch determined by holes stopped by the fingers. These instruments were so hard to blow that the players wore bands over their cheeks, because there were cases on record where, in the contests, they broke their cheeks by the wind pressure. The flute, or aulos, does not seem to have been used in connection with the sitara at all, and the Greeks had nothing corresponding to what we call an orchestra. The aulos was appropriate to certain religious services and to certain festivals, and it had a moderate status in the various contests of the national games, but the great instrument of Greek music, the universal dependence for all occasions, public and private, was the lyre. In spite of the meager resources of Greek music upon its tonal side, this development of art has had a very important bearing upon the progress of music, even down to our own times. Opera was rediscovered about 1600 in the effort to recreate the Greek musical drama, and the ideal proposed to himself by Richard Wagner was nothing else than that of a new music drama in which the severe and lofty conceptions of the old Greek poets should be embodied in musical forms the most advanced that the modern mind has been able to conceive. Upon the aesthetic side, musical theory is entirely indebted to the Greek. Nothing more suitable or appropriate can be said concerning musical taste and cultivation than what was said by Aristotle 300 years before Christ. For example, he has the following, Politics 8, C. Jowett's translation, page 245. The customary branches of education are in number four. They are, 1. Reading and writing, 2. Gymnastic exercises, 3. Music, to which is somewhat added, 4. Drawing. Of these, reading, writing and drawing are regarded as useful to the purposes of life in a variety of ways. He recommends the study of music as part of the preparation of the fit occupation of leisure. There remains, then, the use of music for the intellectual enjoyment of leisure, which appears to have been the reason of its introduction, this being one of the ways in which it is thought that a free man should pass his leisure, As Homer says how good it is to invite men to the pleasant feast, and afterwards he speaks of others whom he describes as inviting the bard who would delight them all. Odyssey 17, 385. And in another place he says that there is no better way of passing life than when men's hearts are merry and the banqueters in the hall sitting in order hear the voice of the minstrel. Plato is particular that only the noble harmonies shall be permitted in his state. He says, Of the harmonies I want to have, one warlike, which will sound the word or note which a brave man utters in the hour of danger or stern resolve, or when his cause is failing and he is going to wounds or death, or is overtaken by some other evil, and in every such crisis meets fortune with calmness and endurance, and another which may be used by him in times of peace and freedom of action, when there is no pressure of necessity, expressive of entreaty, or persuasion, or prayer to God, or of instruction to man, or again willingness to listen to persuasion or entreaty or advice. These two harmonies I ask you to leave, the strain of necessity and the strain of freedom, the strain of the unfortunate and the strain of the fortunate, the strain of courage and the strain of temperance. These I say leave. These, he explains, will be only the Dorian and the Phrygian harmonies. In another place Plato shows himself a disciple of the Egyptian ideas of conservatism already And therefore, when one of these clever and multiformed gentlemen, who can imitate anything, comes to our state, and proposes to exhibit himself and his poetry, we will fall down and worship him as a sweet and holy and wonderful being, but we must also inform him that there is no place for such as he in our state. The law will not allow him. And so when we have anointed him with myrrh and set a garland of wool upon his head, we shall send him away to another city, Republic, Jowat, 3, 398. In fact, upon the subject of music, Plato is one of the least satisfactory of writers. He has many noble sentiments which might well be printed in letters of gold and hung upon the walls of educational institutions today as laws, Jowat's translation, 668, those who seek for the best kind of song and music ought not to seek for that which is pleasant, but for that which is true. In another place, however, he speaks of music as a kind of imitation. He says that music without words is very difficult to understand, laws, Ibid, 668. All these inconsistencies disappear, however, as soon as we recognize the limitations of the music which Plato knew upon its tonal side. All the richness of sense, incitation, and all the definiteness of expression which come into our modern music through the magic of tones in key were wholly outside the range of Plato's knowledge. The musical notation of the Greeks consisted of letters of the alphabet placed over the syllables to which the tones indicated were to be sung. The letters represented absolute pitch, and as owing to the variety of genera, modes, and croa, the total number of tones was very large. Parts of older forms of the alphabet were also employed. The whole number of characters thus demanded being upwards of 70. There was little or no classification of tones, and the entire 24 letters were applied in regular order to the diatonic series of the Dorian mode. Tones in the chromatic or inharmonic modes were named by other letters, and the system was extremely complicated. The notes of the instrumental accompaniment were still different from those of the vocal part. No genuine example of this music has come down to us in reliable form, and curiously enough, no classical writer gives any idea of the notation of music. All that we know of this notation we derive from Alippius, who lived about 150 AD. Athanasius Kircher, a Jesuit of a monastery in Sicily, published in the last century the text of what purported to be a fragment of the first pithic ode of Pindar, see page 69. In the original, the musical characters stood in immediate proximity to the words of the text. At the middle of the third line begins the chorus of sitarodists. As all the musical characters of the Greeks indicated absolute pitch, the student will discover the difference between the vocal and instrumental notation by comparing the notes in the early part of the ode with those of the same pitches noted for instruments later. Three other pieces of similar apocryphal character have come down to us. It is likely that these melodies, if not really genuine as related to the composition of Pindar, nevertheless belong to a period a little anterior to the Christian era. Fragment of the First Pithic Ode of Pindar According to the musical notation given by Athanasius Kircher, F. A. Gewertz, La Musique dans l'Antiquit\u00e9. Listen. Pithic Ode Pithic Ode Pithic Ode Pithic Ode Note. The amateur unfamiliar with the C clef will obtain a true tonal effect of the above fragment from Pindar by considering the clef to be G and the signature five flats. This will transpose the piece one degree lower than above written, but the melody will be preserved, in other words, read it exactly like the treble part of any piano piece, only considering the signature to be five flats. End of chapter 3"
}
